<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>Rowan Manning’s Blog</title>
    <link href="http://rowanmanning.co.uk/blog.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://rowanmanning.co.uk/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-16T16:37:21.720Z</updated>
    <id>http://rowanmanning.co.uk/blog.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Rowan Manning</name>
    </author>

    
        <entry>
            <title>Accessibility: Beyond The Screen-Reader</title>
            <link href="http://rowanmanning.co.uk/posts/accessibility-beyond-the-screen-reader"/>
            <updated>2012-06-06T22:05:00.000Z</updated>
            <id>http://rowanmanning.co.uk/posts/accessibility-beyond-the-screen-reader</id>
            <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Accessibility: Beyond The Screen-Reader&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iʼd like to begin this post with a disclaimer: Iʼm not an accessibility expert. In fact, web accessibility scares me; itʼs that daunting consideration when kicking off a web project that can send shivers down the spines of the hardiest developers. Luckily, us web folk love a challenge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to talk about the common misunderstanding that accessibility means catering for blind people almost exclusively. Iʼve found myself frustrated by “accessibility tunnel-vision” on a number of occasions recently which has me inspired to explain &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; understanding of web accessibility. Who exactly are we trying to cater for? Weʼll start with the obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Blind Or Part-Sighted Users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the user that we tend to jump to when accessibility is mentioned. These users may rely completely on assistive technology, such as a screen-reader, to access the web. Part-sighted or vision-impaired users may not rely on a screen-reader, but will find it difficult to read content if the type is too small or cannot be zoomed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a wealth of resources available to help make our websites work well for this group. In order to achieve a basic level of support, it helps to ensure that your website is usable in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://lynx.browser.org/&quot; title=&quot;The Lynx Browser&quot;&gt;text-based browser such as Lynx&lt;/a&gt; – writing sensible, semantic markup is a first step. I also canʼt emphasise what an eye-opener it is to &lt;a href=&quot;http://webaim.org/articles/screenreader_testing/&quot; title=&quot;Testing with Screen Readers: Questions and Answers&quot;&gt;try and use a screen-reader yourself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vision impaired users can be catered for by keeping your type sizes sensible (personal preference: &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=16px&lt;/code&gt;), and ensuring that your content is zoom-able. Youʼll make this a lot easier by using a scalable font measurement in your CSS such as &lt;code&gt;em&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;rem&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Colour-Blind Users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colour-blind users may find it hard to distinguish between elements on a page if they are similar in colour. This can become a problem when the contrast between two elements is important; for example, between your website text and background. People with even mild colour-blindness may find it difficult to read content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to catering for colour-blind users, subtlety becomes your enemy; there are some great &lt;a href=&quot;http://snook.ca/technical/colour_contrast/colour.html&quot; title=&quot;Colour Contrast Checking Tool&quot;&gt;contrast checking tools online&lt;/a&gt; which can help you immensely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Users With Physical Disabilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical disabilities can encompass anything from minor impairments of motor-skills to paralysis. Motor impairments are common in elderly web users who may rely on a keyboard alone to browse the web – it can be difficult to operate a mouse which requires small, precise hand movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that your website is keyboard-accessible is important, itʼs also quite easy to test: unplug your mouse! There are quite a few resources around the web on this topic, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.456bereastreet.com/archive/201104/keyboard_accessibility_again/&quot; title=&quot;Some useful quick-tips on keyboard accessibility&quot;&gt;fixing up your website for keyboard users&lt;/a&gt; is actually relatively easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Users With Cognitive Disabilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive disabilities get little air-time in my opinion, yet conditions such as dyslexia are extremely common. The diversity of this group is huge, and cognitive disabilities can have an adverse effect on memory; problem solving; attention; and reading, linguistic and verbal comprehension to name a few:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;

    &lt;dt&gt;Memory&lt;dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;Some users may have difficulties with their long, mid or short-term memories. This can be an issue when moving through a stepped sign-up or purchasing process for example. Clear sign-posting and guidance is essential for these users.&lt;/dd&gt;

    &lt;dt&gt;Problem solving&lt;dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;For users who have trouble problem-solving, things like form errors or unclear instructions are a nightmare. Instructions should be clear and large changes to the page should be explained to the user.&lt;/dd&gt;

    &lt;dt&gt;Attention&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;Users with conditions such as &lt;abbr title=&quot;Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder&quot;&gt;ADHD&lt;/abbr&gt; can struggle with concentration at the best of times. Avoiding background noise on a page and using visual cues to highlight important content helps these users.&lt;/dd&gt;

    &lt;dt&gt;Reading, linguistic and verbal comprehension&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;This broad category ranges from problems understanding long or complex words and sentence structure, to difficulty processing non-literal text such as sarcasm, metaphor or slang. Clear document structure, supplemental media and uncomplicated writing can help these users a lot.&lt;/dd&gt;

&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, I can't recommend this &lt;a href=&quot;http://webaim.org/articles/cognitive/&quot; title=&quot;In-depth article on cognitive disabilities and the web&quot;&gt;article on cognitive disabilities&lt;/a&gt; enough. It goes into far more depth than I could on the subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #f00;&quot;&gt;Todo: write this&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        </entry>
    

</feed>